Today's lecture will focus
on genetic evaluations
and long horizon tasks.
How many of you have had to run
an evaluation for your project
to do whatever
you've been doing?
No one is running an evaluation.
How are you guys
doing any projects?
What evaluation tasks have you
used for agentic evaluations?
I'm going to call people
out if I don't get answers.
What have you been
using in your project?
I wonder for agentic
evaluation, do you
mean like it has to be something
like a [INAUDIBLE] bench
or knowledge task or
body of knowledge task?
All of those count.
OK.
Yeah, so then, I guess,
like [INAUDIBLE].
OK, so that's a multi-hop
question answering task.
So [INAUDIBLE] bench
would also count.
What else have you
folks been using?
There's no other answers.
What about you?
Yeah.
I'm working on a private
Wiki for my employer.
And I sat down and
make notes out of that
and then feed that
into a coding agent.
OK, nice.
It's a private Wiki
question/answers.
So I think a lot of this
lecture will focus on
what is challenging
about agentic evaluations
relative to where
things have been before
and how things become harder.
The papers that we'll
cover to cover this topic
will be focused on measuring
the ability of these models
to complete long
tasks in terms of,
what's the length of the task?
Length, as in time
horizon of the task
that the models can complete.
Also second paper
that we'll look at
is GDPVal which was a
recent benchmark that
was released by OpenAI.
This will focus on
how the models perform
on real-world, economically
valuable tasks.
So there has been
a lot of discussion
around the models can do tasks
that real-world professionals
can do.
So this is measuring that
in a very real sense.
And then the last
task will very much
focus on deep
research style tasks.
So it is called
DeepScholar-Bench.
It's out of Stanford.
And it's a live benchmark that
focus on generative research
synthesis.
So it takes a bunch
of papers and then
tries to write the related
work section, a task
that I have always wanted
the language models to go
do for the papers that I write.
So this actually measures
how good of a job
does the model do in
solving these kind of tasks?
So one of the
challenges of measuring
intelligence or progress
of AI is that we
have to measure what matters.
How are the models progressing?
So when we started about
four or five years ago,
even the fact that the models
could generate any explanations
was such a big deal.
And now we measure
the progress of AI
in terms of whether
we can forecast
how it will influence economics
or how it will influence safety.
Traditional benchmarks,
which involve chatbots
or which involve, say,
question/answering or single
shot just answering something
that was already in the context
are starting to saturate
it fairly quickly.
However, we do need to
measure, both in terms
of capability and economic
impact, how these models are
progressing so that we can
see what their impact will
be in the coming years.
So in terms of
measuring capability,
what we covered today is we are
looking at the task, of how long
or how complex of a task
can these models accomplish?
And the second
question we ask is,
what is the economic
value of the task
that these models can do?
Or can they do real-world tasks
that humans can currently do?
And the two papers that
we are referencing here
is-- or the two metrics
that we are referencing here
is that METR refers to the
time horizon metric calibrated
by human professionals.
And GDPVal compares the win
rate of model performing
a task relative to experts.
So both of them are equally
valid metrics in certain ways.
And the insights
are very similar.
But the trends that they measure
in terms of how models perform
are quite different.
So let's start
with the first one.
So, when you're
talking to a chatbot,
if you were talking to a
chatbot, say three, four,
or five years ago, usually
after a first couple of rounds
in multi-turn conversation,
the model will be lost.
It doesn't keep context of what
you were talking to it about.
Today as you talk
to these models,
the conversation
can go pretty long.
So it does keep that context.
And that relates then
to the question of,
what is the duration of the task
that the model can complete.
So that's just the
duration question.
And then the second question is,
what's the percentage success?
Can it do so reliably?
So METR, this
particular benchmark
focuses on duration of the
task that model can complete.
And then it associates a
reliability metric of like,
will it complete it
with 50% success or will
it complete it with 80% success?
And so on.
And the universal
anchor for these tasks
ends up being the,
how much time will it
take humans to complete
if they were professionals
in solving these tasks?
So there are three
task suites that
are used to design this
particular benchmark.
One is extremely small.
So one to 30 seconds.
It basically focusing
on just atomic actions.
So in software engineering,
can you open a file?
Can you do something small?
The second one is HCAST,
which focuses on more 1 minute
to 30 hours style of
tasks, which is basically
talking about different software
and research engineering tasks.
And then finally, RE-Bench
that's actually giving a full ML
research style tasks, which can
go on as long as eight hours.
So you've seen like AI scientist
paper covered in this class
before.
So similar style of benchmarks.
In total, it covers
about 170 tasks
going all the way from say,
one seconds to eight hours.
So if you were to look at
this, in terms of a division,
you will see that HCAST
has about 97 tasks.
These are the 1 minute
to 30 hour tasks.
SWAA has about 66 tasks.
And then RE-Bench, which are
more research engineering
tasks that take much longer
are about seven tasks.
So the first they do is
they collect these tasks,
they vet the set of
tasks that go into each
of these benchmark suites.
Then they actually have time
estimates from both human
doing the task and then
the agent doing the task.
From human runs, they actually
estimate the amount of time
it takes the human to
complete that task,
and whether they found
it difficult or not.
And then for the agent,
they're measuring whether they
completed it reliably or not.
And finally, based on
enough data points,
they fit a curve which measures
the success rate versus the time
estimate.
And based on that, they
find the time horizon
for these models
completing the tasks.
So that gives a sense of the
horizon length relative to model
release dates.
So what we'll see
in terms of trends
are, for models released
on different dates, roughly
what is the time horizon with
which the models complete
the tasks?
50% of the time or
ti 80% of the time?
Questions.
What is a task that takes
you guys a couple of minutes?
And what's a task that takes
you guys say a couple of hours
that you think you would like
to delegate to the models?
Writing the literature
review section of the paper.
Yes.
That usually takes
several hours.
So that would be a great task.
And that would fall somewhere
in the HCAST or RE-Bench task.
Any other takers
relative to what you do?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] for each reference.
Say that again.
Double-check [INAUDIBLE].
So in the paper writing,
you want the BibTeX item
to be correct.
So you want it to go
query the right websites
and find the BibTeX item.
How many minutes do you
think that should take?
So it falls more in that
one-- the HCAST style,
like diverse tasks?
OK.
Cool.
Any other tasks that people
think that the model should
be good at?
OK.
I think [INAUDIBLE]
should be faster.
So refactoring the codebase
can be large or can be small.
Yeah, it depends on
what the refractor.
What the refactor requires.
If the logic stays the same and
it's just moving around code,
then that perhaps is a few
hours can be a couple of days.
Someone has to check
correctness of that as well.
Makes sense.
So that one will fall perhaps
like closer to RE-Bench.
One can imagine that there
will be a version of just
like the coding-related tasks.
Cool.
OK.
So for the second step,
for the human [INAUDIBLE],
so for a certain type of task,
for these types [INAUDIBLE]
human beings [INAUDIBLE]
some people do it faster.
Some people do it slower.
So I'm just wondering,
so on one extreme case,
you just have one main evaluator
and then you have just one
[INAUDIBLE].
On the other extreme,
you have 100 generations.
You have distribution.
And you can compare where
the algorithm stands.
So I'm just curious
where that's most
of the individual performance.
So typically, what is
done with most of the--
I mean, getting a lot of experts
to solve the task is relatively
expensive.
So typically, you will have
a few experts solve the task
and then you look for
inter-rater agreement
or inter-human agreement
in this particular case.
And what you're saying
is that generally,
if the numbers are
very far off, then
you go get more data points.
And if there's general
agreement, then you move on.
So just the example
of task, just related
to what the class talked about,
where you wanted the literature
review section or
you wanted the BibTeX
being accurately classified
or the refactoring
of the code base.
Some of the example tasks
of different durations
that were in this paper
are find a shell script.
So that's perhaps just
take three seconds.
Or Wikipedia research.
This is closer to the research
section that you wanted.
Or another one is detect and
fix a bug in the input files
for a simulation, so that takes
like 10 minutes for a human.
Then there is munging of data.
So data munging
task where you're
transforming some JSON data
from one format to another.
And then Cuda backtesting
tool, which basically you
are implementing.
Custom Cuda kernels
can take tens of hours
to here it's like
eight hours and they
are aiming for a certain
performance improvement.
So all of these tests are part
of this particular benchmark.
And the way-- this
actually addresses
the question you
were asking, the way
they are going about getting
the human baseline for task
completion is that
they go and get
skilled professionals with
roughly five years of experience
in the field to record
their completion
times for successful attempts.
And then they take a geometric
mean for the task difficulty
rating based on the humans
that went and solved this.
One challenge with
this is that people
who are experienced in the
field are conditioned to what it
means to be successful in this.
So they will often
underestimate the difficulty
of the task, which
might not correlate
to how the model sees whether
this task is difficult or not.
So in terms of trends, what
they found is, on the x-axis,
we have the human
time to complete.
And on the y-axis, we
have the success rate
going all the way from 0 to 1.
So the model success rate for--
if you look at smaller tasks
like 1 to 30 second tasks, which
are the SWAA tasks
or the green tasks,
that's generally
on the higher side.
For HCAST tasks,
which are basically
the tasks which are diverse
tasks going all the way from
say few minutes
to several hours,
that's all over the place.
So it's anywhere from 0.8 being
the highest all the way to 0.
And then the RE-Bench
tasks have some success,
but tend to be on the lower
side at this point in time.
There have been papers saying
that they are making progress
on RE-Bench tasks,
but generally,
it's a much harder task in terms
of the human time to complete,
it takes long.
And then the model success
rate is also fairly low.
So the longer the
task, the harder
it's for models to stay
on track and complete.
And this is partly why agentic
evaluations and what you measure
starts to become a
challenging aspect.
In terms of trends,
if you were to--
we chatted about
the fact that if you
were to query these models
about 2019 when GPT-2 came out,
typically, the models would
really just address tasks
that were two seconds long.
So on the y-axis, you have
the task time for completion
with 50% success rate.
So it doesn't have to
be completely reliable.
So in 2019 when GPT-2 came
out, only two seconds.
Closer to GPT-4,
which is 2023, you're
starting to see a few minutes.
And when we have Claude 3.7
Sonnet and o1, at that point,
you're starting to
see a few hours.
Now note that this is
almost like a doubling
because this is--
so it's doubling
every seven months.
But the other thing
to note here is
that even though these
tasks are being completed,
the reliability is not high.
They only being completed
50% of the time.
So that's like saying that you
gave your task to an intern,
but it only completes
it 50% of the time.
So it might come back with
an answer or it might not.
So there's always some
amount of uncertainty.
So this is just
making the same point
that going from GPT-2, which was
just two seconds to GPT-4, which
was like eight minutes, now
Claude 3.7 Sonnet in 2025
can go all the way to 59
minutes with 50% success rate.
And what is really
driving this improvement?
So some of the
capabilities that we're
seeing in the model that
are really helpful in terms
of driving these improvements
are better logical reasoning.
So the models can--
we've covered a lot of
previous lectures on the models
learn how to reason better.
So the reasoning
capabilities definitely drive
some of these improvements.
Code generation
capabilities have improved.
So we have covered
several lectures
where you've seen the models do
better on the code generation
side.
So that's definitely driving
some of these improvements.
Too use.
So we covered React
and several papers
around just how the
models use tools.
So that also has added up.
And then in general,
there has been
a focus on getting these
models to be more reliable so
that they're not repetitive in
just repeating the same behavior
over and over again.
And finally, you want these
models to generally recover
from errors.
I mean, if you're going
to do an eight-hour task,
you're going to have some steps
which are going to be wrong.
So you have to recover
from those errors,
and you need a better awareness
of, what is your final goal?
And some notion of
state of or memory of,
what is the final goal?
And how far along are you
in terms of making progress
towards that goal?
Other aspects of
what folks have seen
as driving these improvements.
Any comments?
Why do you think Claude Code
does better today relative
to say, last year?
How many people use
Claude Code or Codex?
There's a new trend for
context engineering.
People are just learning how to
structure the context better,
so that the tooling just
becomes better and improves
to make the improvements.
So what you're
saying is, I'm just
repeating for the class,
that context engineering
or being able to structure
the context better
over multiple time steps
is starting to improve,
which also helps.
Thank you.
You see that
compaction window that
happens when Claude basically
gets to the end of its context.
Yes.
I think just like maybe from
feedback of actual people
using it.
And then I know
that for a cursor,
they have online URLs,
right, for tab completions.
So maybe, I don't know for how
that works with board for Claude
Code, but I guess,
supposedly they
get some sort of
feedback from the user
logs and then try to either
back-propagate [INAUDIBLE]
or just kind of figuratively
in the workflow.
So generally, address
the class of problems
that are starting to show up.
Yes.
So when problems [INAUDIBLE] So
when problems are really complex
now is the coding agents usually
trigger explicit planning stuff.
So that kind of helps to plan
when problems are re-occurring.
And so they stick to the plan.
And this kind of reduces some
trial and error with experience.
Nice.
So what you're
saying is that if you
look at where the
problem is very complex,
the model as a first
step does some planning.
So it breaks down the
problem into multiple steps.
And oftentimes, when it goes
and executes some of the steps,
it might actually
trigger re-planning.
So it might actually come
up with a new set of steps
to go do based on the
data it's collected.
That's very good insight.
So when you use Claude Code,
sometimes the code has anger.
I mean, the Claude
Code, it seems
the code that has a problem.
So it's [INAUDIBLE] the user
may use [INAUDIBLE] copy paste
the code, the editor
to the Claude code
and them Claude Code will know
that code has [INAUDIBLE].
So that means that [INAUDIBLE]
it's similar to [INAUDIBLE].
Yes.
So there's always
the user feedback
where the user says what
you gave me is not right.
So then the model
has to redo the job.
That's same as
doing like someone
has given you an assignment.
And then if it's not
to the satisfaction,
you've got to redo.
That's fair.
How does memory play
out in all of this?
Or context, what's in context?
We covered, like we had a
whole lecture on memory.
Why is memory important?
OK.
So sometimes the agent
has like atomic memory
knows [INAUDIBLE] about
understanding of code base.
So this kind of
sampling from theory
and updating the
[INAUDIBLE] priors,
so it knows better like
what the environment looks
like [INAUDIBLE] expected.
OK.
So what he's saying is
that sometimes the agent
might actually
need to understand
what the environment is better.
So for example, an
understanding of the code bases.
So having memory helps
keep that understanding
if it's going to operate
over a similar code base.
OK, thank you.
OK, let's keep going.
So now let's take a look at
reliability aspect of it.
So capability is
only one axis along
which we want these
models to do better.
Reliability is the other one.
So what we are
measuring here is again
x-axis is the
model release date.
And now we want to see how the
models do at 80% success rate.
So the gray line is the
50% reliability one.
And then the blue line
is the 80% success rate.
And y-axis is the time
taken by the models
to complete the tasks.
So what you see here is
that while we were claiming
that you can get all the
way up to 59 minutes in 2025
with the latest and
greatest models, if you want
high reliability, you are
still at a few minutes
or maybe tens of minutes.
And so to get 80% success
rate with the models,
there is a big delta
between the 59 minutes
that we were claiming
with the best model
versus at 80%
success rate, you're
still closer to say, somewhere
around 8 to 10 minutes.
So big delta roughly
tells you that there's
a lot of headroom to make
in terms of reliability
so that the model comes back and
is successful most of the time.
Yes.
So do you [INAUDIBLE]
based on your experience?
Let's ask that question
at the end of the lecture
because you will
have a lot more--
I mean, the whole
lecture was about this.
I just wonder what
paper is this part from?
This is from the paper--
paper is posted online.
The first paper, right?
Yeah.
Both the paper and
the slides are online.
So basically, 80%
horizon is still
showing doubling time,
similar time horizons.
But it is saying that you have--
it's five weeks shorter.
So the 15 minutes
is what Claude 3.7
can achieve 80% of
the time versus 59
minutes 50% of the time.
So this gap, basically,
says that if you're
trying to deploy these models
in real-world tasks, then
there will be reliability
challenges even
for moderately complex tasks.
So that requires--
there's definitely
a lot of headroom in
how we build systems
on top of these models.
And an important
question to ask is,
what are the kind
of failures that we
run into with these models?
And this is looking
at both GPT-4,
which is a non-reasoning
model and o1, which
is a reasoning model.
Now this paper is a bit
older and you can refer
to things that are a bit newer.
But at the same time,
the kind of failure modes
are very similar in many cases.
So we can take a look here.
So the kind of failure
modes that they found
are closer to either
poor planning.
So the model doesn't know
how to break the task.
It was given down into steps.
Poor tool choice.
So the set of tools that
it tries to choose here
may or may not be correct.
And there were errors along both
these axes in the GPT-4 and o1.
A second failure type
is incorrect mental math
or reasoning.
Style tasks.
So here the model
is basically doing
some sort of math or reasoning,
but it's doing it incorrectly.
Another failure type
is that prematurely, it
abandons the tasks
because it goes
around some repetitive
behavior, but is not
quite able to figure out
what it means for the task
to be successful.
Another failure mode is that
the model will basically
get into a repetitive
loop, so it will basically
go do some actions.
And then that's still the
highest probability action
even after it has failed.
So it then goes and
does that action again.
So it might basically
be with high probability
repeating the same action.
So with GPT-4, this
was a pretty high.
For o1, this has become lower.
And then there's other category
of tasks that they showed--
there are other categories
of failures that they
showed are also prevalent.
But this gives you
a sense of planning,
tool choice,
reasoning errors, not
being able to figure out
when the task is completed,
and then just
repetitive loops tend
to be some of the failure
modes for these models.
And failure mode analysis is
very useful in understanding
where the models can
or cannot improve.
This is a common way, is
that typically [INAUDIBLE].
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
Not similar categories, but it's
common to evaluate the models.
And then if you're saying
that you have a challenging
benchmark, then
you would showcase,
where do the models fail?
What is the common
failure pattern?
[INAUDIBLE]
Human reader or
self-inflicted pain.
So you evaluate
the model yourself
and see where it's failing.
I think we have been asking you
guys to do that for homeworks.
When you go actually try to do
the self iterative refinement
loop, then you have to evaluate
where the model failed.
OK.
So some of the challenges
in this benchmark.
So no benchmark is ever perfect.
Every benchmark has
some challenges.
So some of the things that
[INAUDIBLE] did get right
is that it's the first
attempt at measuring,
what is the time
horizon of tasks
that these models can complete?
And some of the challenges that
the model does not quite solve
is that it has lower performance
on tasks that are messy,
where there's not one
single correct answer
or there is some amount
of complexity involved.
But if you have some
amount of messiness then,
similar trends will be there
at in different categories
of tasks.
Another one is that if you
try to look at SWE-bench,
SWE-bench has a similar
trend to what we were showing
in all the plots before,
but the annotators generally
underestimates SWE-bench.
And the models also have seen
most of the GitHub repositories.
So a lot of the estimates
that are made on SWE-bench
tend to be shorter in
terms of doubling time
relative to if it was a
completely unseen repository.
A third challenge
with the benchmark
is that if you actually have
internal pull requests-- so this
is for internal code bases,
then what has been found
is that if you put
contractors on the job,
people who don't have context,
who have not been working
on that code base, versus you
put code maintainers on the job.
The contractors can be anywhere
from 5 to 18 times slower.
And model performance
is consistent
closer to contractor times
because it's basically never
seen that code base before.
So this suggests that when
you're dealing with these models
going and solving these tasks,
this is still very valuable.
But at the same time,
it's operating more
as not someone who is
an expert in that area
or has the context of that area.
It's more as a low
context human who's
basically been asked
to solve that problem,
similar to a contractor.
So that's summarizing
the first paper.
But hopefully, that
gives you a flavor
of when we are measuring
the progress in AI,
one of the axes in
agentic evaluations
that becomes important
is to measure,
how long are the tasks that
the AI can complete reliably?
Any questions or comments before
we move to the next section?
OK.
So the next paper
that we will look at
is GDPVal, which is
evaluating the model
performance on real-world
economically valuable tasks.
So instead of asking the
question, can AI do this?
Where you have a task that
you want to delegate to AI.
Hear the question
is very much around,
if we were to give this task to
the model instead of a human,
is the output good enough?
And the win rate
will be directly
against industry experts.
So it will actually take--
the task suite is designed
as real work from
professionals who
have more than a decade of
experience in their fields.
So you will see here that
the kind of professions
that were used for
task suite design
are pretty broad ranging here.
So it goes anywhere
from say real estate,
where you take a broad
range of tasks to government
to manufacturing,
professional, scientific,
and technical services,
healthcare, finance, retail,
wholesale, and information,
including film and video
editors.
So it's actually a pretty
broad range of tasks.
And given the models
have become multimodal,
this is does make sense.
The models will not be
good at all of these tasks.
They will only be good at some
of these tasks, of course.
So let's take a look at
some example tasks here.
And also think about
the tasks that you
think that the models
might be good at as you
go through this list.
So in manufacturing engineer,
it's being asked to design a 3D
model of a cable reel
stand for assembly line.
In financial and
investment analysts,
it's being asked to create
the competitive landscape.
So it's a research heavy task.
In registered nurse,
it's basically
assessing the images of issue
and creating a consultation
report.
In film and video
editor, it's asking
to create an intro reel
given some sort of script.
In customer service,
it's being asked
to draft an email response
for dissatisfied customer.
In concierge, it's basically
creating an itinerary
for a family of four.
In audit, it's
basically figuring out
pricing inconsistencies between
given a few different purchase
orders.
For a real estate agent, it's
designing a sales brochure
for a new property.
And then recreation
worker, it's basically
asked to optimize the
layout of vendor fair?
What do people think?
These are very real
tasks, actually sourced
from professionals
in their fields.
Very interesting, right?
May things are very
subjective to evaluate.
Very subjective
to evaluate, yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, what I do is going
to may not be what you do.
Yeah.
So that's why the success
metric will be win rate.
It's not like if you put
humans on the job versus you
put models on the job,
what is the win rate?
And there might
be specific style
that the model chooses
that doesn't quite
hold for all cases.
Yes, so it's objective.
And at the same time, that
subjective nature also
makes one of the challenges.
That's why real-world
work requires
both context and subjectivity
in how things get evaluated.
What are other real-world
tasks that people
have seen that are
interesting related to this?
You brought up about--
you put private Wiki
QA and use that to query the
knowledge base in your job?
That's feeding into coding even,
what we're finding is actually
better finding dead
parts of the Wiki
that are no longer
useful [INAUDIBLE].
Thanks.
Any other ideas from the class?
[INAUDIBLE]
Other tasks, yeah.
So doctors-- no, I
mean, it has no respect.
I feel for controversial
topics is not there.
For example, [INAUDIBLE] or
other [INAUDIBLE] based on those
context are following
requirements.
So I think [INAUDIBLE] here.
For example, there are tasks--
I think we should separate out.
There's definitely a question
around whether the models are
good at it and whether we
want to use them for ethics
and actual compliance reasons.
So I think those two questions
need to be separated out
from what models can do today.
So this is more about,
is the model output
good enough in the
subjective areas?
I'm trying to see if
our doctors-- so there's
registered nurses.
There's a lot of tasks.
But they put registered
nurses and nurse practitioners
in healthcare more than doctors.
What about for
people [INAUDIBLE]
for the information
science, they
don't mention like computation.
Say that again.
Compose a song, compose
a song for someone.
OK.
So yes, that's correct.
So maybe that's an emerging
task that will show up.
But that's not part of
this benchmark just yet.
Here's one comment on that.
Maybe for the music,
composing music,
the verification is
quite subjective,
or it's harder to say, I guess,
you can make [INAUDIBLE] music
and all of them, it's
hard to differentiate.
And maybe whether you're
trying to hear is it,
so that they can--
there is a deliverable
that's fairly clear if
it is working or not.
So top-down, this dataset,
this evaluation dataset targets
about nine sectors.
And they actually went
for top 5% of the GDP.
So they're asking, what
are the most economically
valuable tasks?
And whether the models
are good enough at that.
They cover about 44 occupations
and sourced about 1,320 tasks
through that.
And 200 of them or 220
of them are actually
in an open goal set that
is on hugging phase.
Predominantly went
for digital tasks.
So tasks on computer
which is 60% of the--
so O*NET is a taxonomy of
all tasks that are related
to occupations.
So 60% of the O*NET tasks that
are computer-based and digital
made it into this
evaluation dataset.
And this basically is a
pretty representative coverage
of various set of tasks
that an occupational expert
will need to do in these
particular sectors.
And in terms of the
characteristics of tasks
that people went
after, they might
have as long as seven hours
of completion time on average,
but some might require weeks.
The tasks were both
text-based and multimodal.
So like CAD, video, audio,
spreadsheets, presentations.
The average value of the task,
at least in the gold subset,
was anywhere from
say $400 per task.
But if anyone has
seen cvLancer, there's
also much higher value tasks.
So this one also has high
value and low value tasks.
Many of these tasks,
about 70% of these tasks,
require interaction
with the reference file.
So you have to interact
with some reference files
to arrive at a final output.
And all of these tasks were
vetted through experts.
So about 89% of the tasks were
actually vetted by experts
as being very well specified.
So they were not
like ill specified
and extremely hard
for the model just
because they're ill specified.
So if you look at the
trend, so on the x-axis,
now you see different models
all the way from GPT-4o to GPT-5
high to Claude Opus 4.1.
And on the y-axis,
you're looking
at win rate versus the
industry professionals.
So basically, if
you had an expert
with more than a decade
of experience solving it
versus the model solving it.
So light blue is wins plus ties
and dark blue is wins only.
There's a pairwise preferences.
So if you look at
GPT-4o on an average,
the average numbers don't
mean that every single task
was solved like that.
Go anywhere from say
12.4%, so that's 2024,
to it starts to get to 25.
And then more recently,
it is in the 30s.
And then now with Claude Opus
4.1, it starts to get to 47.6.
So that's a very
different trend compared
to METR where we were talking
about this doubling trend
every seven months.
It's more of a
linear trend roughly
compared to the
exponential trend
that METR was talking about.
And at the same time,
this is real work
where you are comparing
relative to an expert.
So the measurement
is very much based
on whether this task, whether
the model output was good
enough or not.
So the reliability or rather
the model output being useful
matters here.
Questions.
Yes.
This trend is directly
comparable to the meter one,
though, because
here the y-axis win
rate for industry professionals
as opposed to the time horizon
that's in the other case.
So yeah, should I really think
about them as disagreeing?
I wouldn't say that
disagreeing was wrong
because they're measuring
different metric, as we
said early on.
But I think what it's
roughly emphasizing
is that when you see
an exponential trend,
people often assume that OK,
so now AI can do one hour.
So next, it will be able
to do a couple of hours.
And the next, it will be
able to do a couple of days.
So there's that exponential
trend that gets people.
What this is saying
is that if you
look at tasks that require
say several hours or a couple
of days or a couple of weeks,
then the models are only
so reliable in doing that and
it's actually breaking it down
by profession.
So it kind of makes
it more realistic
by nailing it down not
just by numbers of hours,
but more by this is real work.
And can the AI
models do it or not?
Other comments?
Yeah.
I think this chart is like on
the aggregate level across all
the professions.
We will look at the
specific ones as well.
So there might be maybe ones
that are more susceptible,
where, I guess--
Another set of comments
with respect to, say,
the model-specific
trends is that it always
tends to be better at, say,
aesthetics, document formatting,
understanding PDFs,
spreadsheets, and presentations,
while GPT-5 often tends to be
better at, say, instruction
following, correct calculations,
and just text-based tasks.
So that's something
that was noticed
by this particular evaluation.
And then if you look
at failure modes, which
is very important to analyze in
most of these benchmarks, then
oftentimes the
common area failure
ends up being
instruction following.
So a lot of the blue bars show
different instruction following
errors in different models.
Oftentimes, the
models will promise
to look at the reference
data, but then actually not
look at it.
They will override it with
whatever hallucination
they want to come up with.
And then there's also
formatting errors
that tend to be a
bit of a problem,
with, GPT-5 tends to have
fewer instruction following
error is what was measured
by this particular benchmark.
Related to the reference data,
so our next particular section
of the lecture will actually
discuss more about that, being
able to consult a knowledge
base or reference data
and why that's an
important skill to go test.
And then in terms more
on the failure modes.
So this was basically
measuring whether GPT-5,
if you look at the percentage
of tasks that will generally
be seen as acceptable but
subpar, if you delegated
that task to the model.
What they found was that
roughly half the tasks were
acceptable, but subpar, but
then only 20% of the tasks
fell somewhere like OK, the
model will genuinely be better.
And 29% of the tasks were
like bad or catastrophic,
where the model output was
really not acceptable at all.
And there was some
amount of disagreement
between human
graders with respect
to whether they agree on what
the assessment of the model
output is or not.
So that also affects
some of this analysis.
And then another
interesting thing
is that it's something
that since this
is a self-improving agent's
class, so a lot of times
if you basically do
parallel sampling.
So if you try something
or sequential sampling
where you do something
n times, then
ask the model to fix itself
based on whatever it was seeing.
That loop can often
really improve.
So what this particular
table is showing
is that you can either
do naive just one trial
or you can do-- sorry,
you can try one time
or you can try n times where
you basically, every single time
you do something, you can
improve the last iteration.
So in terms of
speed improvement,
what they found was that GPT-5
was overall about 1.6x in cost
improvement if you could try
n times and about 1.4 in speed
improvement relative
to an unaided expert.
But there is still
where it's successful,
it is still less than 10%
of the human expert salary.
So there's definitely
some subset of professions
where the models are
doing a pretty strong job
and have the capability to
take on that tasks completely.
So some people also mentioned
exactly which category
We will get that.
That's exactly
where we're going.
So in terms of
performance variation.
So by sectors, in government,
retail, and wholesale,
I think the broad items,
the broad categories
are not that illustrative.
Looking at the a
specific task help.
But they are the--
performance was near parity
relative to human experts.
By duration, the
models were better
at shorter tasks
up to a few hours,
definitely declines
with longer tasks.
And we already discussed
that on modality.
There were some models
were better at multimodal
while others were
better at text.
OK, this is going to be
an extremely dense plot,
but I think the thing to notice
here in all of these plots
is that the red line is
the one where we are saying
the human experts and then
all of these different colors
are corresponding
to different models.
So if you look at places
where the models are better
or at least are almost at
par with the human experts,
you see that counter
and rental clerks.
So some of those tasks have
already started to hit that.
Real estate brokers,
for example.
Shipping, receiving, and
inventory clerks, for example.
Buyers and purchasing agents.
You can imagine why.
Computer and IT
managers are definitely
like it's starting to hit where
an average human expertise would
be.
When I say average this is
not like the best expert
in the field.
And then software
developers definitely are.
A lot of the models are
starting to hit capability
in typical software
engineering tasks.
I'm seeing some
interesting reactions
from students in class.
Can I have some comments?
For the software, I know that
you mentioned previously,
it's like [INAUDIBLE]
14 years of experience.
But software
developer, it can be--
like the range can
be pretty wide.
I think in the case of
software developers,
they probably went for
more of the maintenance
of the repository as opposed
to the decade of experience.
I think there are
fields here where,
I mean, for example, industrial
engineer or mechanical engineer,
the decade of
experience matters.
And software developer,
knowing the software
codebase in and out.
And the then two cases
of that [INAUDIBLE].
OK, this is another
one of those thoughts.
Let's just focus on where
we're seeing the models
do extremely well.
So again, government, the
administrative service managers,
in compliance officers, models
are doing extremely well.
And then in medical and
health service managers,
those tasks, multiple models
are doing extremely well.
In personal financial
advisor and customer service
representatives
also, you're starting
to see that the models are
starting to do extremely well.
But in general, this
gives you a glossary
or a taxonomy set of
tasks that the models are
starting to perform well in.
And if you're looking
at other tasks
where the models
are failing, I think
this is a very good way to
get a starting point on,
what are the models failing at?
Questions or comments?
OK, this is the last
round, I promise.
So first line supervisors
and retail sales workers.
I think in general,
in retail trade,
we are starting to see some
of those tasks taken on
by the [INAUDIBLE] as a useful
thing for non-retail sales
workers.
So in general, on
the sales side.
In terms of editing
tasks, we're seeing
the models do extremely well.
In terms of research-based
tasks, both investigative
and detective-based
and news analysts,
and then sales representatives,
wholesale and manufacturing,
those tasks seem to
suggest that the models are
doing extremely well.
So this gives you a
flavor of the kind
of tasks that the models
are performing strongly at.
Overall, if you
under-specify the prompts.
So if you actually remove
context from the prompt,
then the models do end
up not doing that well.
In their particular case,
there was a few points lower
in terms of win rate.
But in terms of
actual model output,
the models actually struggle
to figure out what to work on.
So there's definitely
some amount
of-- when you're doing
real work and you
can specify all the context
that the human had in their head
to go do the work.
And it's mostly about reasoning
and just going and executing
a certain set of tool calls,
then the models can do the job.
But there's a lot
of figuring out
what needs to be worked on, how
that context needs to be used,
what needs to be in the context.
And a lot of that
doesn't get captured
by the model on its own.
So that's definitely one
area where the humans have
to orchestrate, what is it?
What is the actual
thing to go work on?
So humans are
basically architecting,
what is the set of problems?
And then the model can go
solve it in certain cases.
And this is further
exemplified by what
we covered before where if you
had a repository maintainer
versus an external
contractor, the speed at which
the repository maintainer
is able to solve problems
is generally much faster.
So if you have an expert
who has a domain knowledge,
they will generally
be faster compared
to someone who has no context.
So real work is
often context heavy.
And what we are measuring in
this particular evaluation
is more around, can a
smart person do this?
Or can someone embedded
in this work can do this?
But if you have to go
get context for that task
that models are
not yet able to do,
and this evaluation
is not measuring that.
So in near term,
what this means is
that AI assistance
is already happening
in professional workflows.
We have covered some of
the agentic workflows
in early parts of the lecture.
And it's definitely
cost effective
when you couple it
with human oversight,
like if the humans
are architecting what
the models need to go work on,
the AI assistance is definitely
helping.
In certain occupations, this
is more impactful than not.
But you do have to
choose different models,
and different models are
stronger at different task types
as well.
OK, questions or comments.
Yes.
How much [INAUDIBLE] on the
actual dollar value [INAUDIBLE].
So the tasks?
Yeah.
Why do you ask that question?
Well, because it seems like it's
a relevant way of quantifying
actual economic impact.
You can say, oh, AI can now do
$100,000 of work or something
that.
But if these numbers
are collected
in a way that seems unreliable
or misleading, then [INAUDIBLE].
I think to me, it's not
so much about the dollar.
I mean, they did go after
the top 5% of the GDP tasks.
For the past several
decades, the knowledge work
has been one of the
key areas that has been
the highest paid profession.
And in knowledge work,
there are certain categories
of tasks that the models
will be very good at.
Deep research being one of
them, perhaps, another one
being like code generation.
So in each-- or
understanding a diverse
set of information sources.
So the models will generally
be good at those set of tasks.
So I think the
question I would ask
is, what is the category of
tasks that the models are
likely to be good at?
Just because at any
given point in time,
humans are strong at
certain set of things.
And machines, just
by way of being
able to crunch the
electricity, are just better
at certain set of things.
So this is more
along those lines.
So there's a certain category
of tasks that will definitely
be valuable.
Delegating to the model
is the way to look at it.
And which are the professions
in which those category of tasks
fall?
Is what this benchmark
is showcasing.
Before this benchmark
came out, people
would talk about this
area of like OK, this
is going to impact a
lot of professions,
but there was no
quantitative way
to measure what set of tasks
in each of these professions.
And it seemed like a
humongous task to go do that.
So this is a very
verifiable, quantifiable way
to even have a taxonomy
to list the set of tasks
in each of the professions.
And what does it mean for
the model to go do them?
Earlier, when we
were doing the class,
in the previous
iteration, we were only
talking about ML-Bench and
RE- Bench and given that.
Our backgrounds are, say, more
ML or more research or more
software.
It's easier for us to understand
the progress of these models
in those domains.
I'm just curious, how is
[INAUDIBLE] when the model will
outperform the
human, it just means
like it's human, not
necessary [INAUDIBLE] anymore.
I mean, this is where I
was adding these caveats.
So when a model is
outperforming the human,
you should go look
at the prompt.
And what that's saying
is that for a human who
has a lot of
context, if they were
to specify all the
context in their head
to specify it in a
prompt, then the models
can also do those tasks.
While a lot of actual work
experience or a lot of workplace
challenges often are about
figuring out what to prioritize,
what are the set of
problems to solve,
where to put our resources.
We will move to the last
benchmark, which will be
focused on DeepScholar-Bench.
This was a task that
one of our classmates
requested early on, where they
want AI to write the literature
review section of their paper.
So here we are.
Let's benchmark that task.
This was written at Stanford.
And this is basically
measuring the question of,
instead of asking how long
will the task take to solve,
is the model output good enough?
They're actually asking, can AI
perform deep research synthesis?
Can I go study a
bunch of references
and retrieve the
relevant information
and then synthesize the findings
into a coherent set of reports
and have verifiable citations?
And there have been
several industry prototypes
that have come out.
So there's OpenAI deep
research, Gemini deep research.
Perplexity has a
deep research thing.
Storm is from Stanford.
There is OpenScholar.
You folks built a deep
research agent in homework 3
and maybe you got a flavor
of what that feels like.
So in general, there has been
a lot of research activity
in this area, and it still
continues to be a challenging
area, as what this paper shows.
So the task that
this paper addresses
is to generate the related work
section for academic papers.
The reason they
care about this task
is because this is a
task that most of us
require when we
are writing papers.
And it requires continuous
updates with fresh queries.
So there is not no staleness.
The way they went about
constructing this dataset
is they used recent arXiv
papers with PhD level difficulty
across 22 domains.
And they rerun it monthly with
new papers, so it stays live.
So it's very nice in
that respect as well.
And it avoids data
contamination.
They only look at
papers that are
post-training of a major model.
So that's very nice.
What they're evaluating
the models on
is three particular axes.
So the first thing they're
evaluating the model on
is knowledge synthesis.
So what they're
basically saying that,
is the model output
organizing and is
coherent in organizing the
knowledge that is presenting?
And is it capturing
all the key facts?
So is it capturing
the key nuggets?
This second axes, it's
evaluating the model
on its retrieval quality.
So if it's looking at a
particular set of references,
how relevant they are to what
you wanted to do research on?
For example, if you're
writing a related work
section for your final
project, and you have say,
10 references that this model
or agent went and fetched,
are they relevant
to what you actually
want to present in your
final report or not?
Citation counts.
It's kind of well known that you
want highly authentic sources.
So whether the papers
are important in terms
of covering those
in the retrieval
and then reference coverage.
So this is similar to--
is it finding important
papers or not?
And then the third axis it's
measuring is verifiability.
So, do the citations
support the claims?
So even if it finds
good papers and it's
citing some aspect
of that paper,
is the claim supported
by that citation?
And then, are claims
backed by the citation?
So these two are very similar.
But one is measuring precision
and one is measuring coverage.
And each of these metrics are
actually validated by humans.
So they got about 70% to
80% of human agreement
when they got humans
to evaluate this.
Now the fun thing is that
most benchmarks get saturated.
So when we look at benchmarks,
we are like, OK, well,
it's already at 70% or 80%.
So there is no headroom.
The fun thing about this
particular benchmark
is that none of the existing
systems actually exceeds 19%.
So if this were to show
up in your homework
for the next iteration
of the class,
there's a lot of
headroom for you folks
to actually make
it a final project.
In terms of, if you look at
each of these axes on which they
are breaking down the
model performance,
in terms of knowledge
synthesis, they
found that OpenAI deep research
does a pretty good job,
but almost all of the models
consistently miss key facts.
So even though they
write coherently.
So it's great English,
but not necessarily
covering all the key facts.
The retrieval quality
tends to be overall OK.
So all systems
currently struggle
to find comprehensive and
important set of sources.
The document importance in all
of them is less than 12.5%.
And then finally, if you
look at verifiability,
they found that say DeepScholar
base got up to 90% precision.
But OpenAI deep research
has lower verifiability,
despite the fact that it
does a really good job
at writing really nice English.
So the synthesis is
extremely coherent.
Now, if you look at
the failure modes,
and that's where a lot
of the learnings lie.
Typically, the failure
modes come from not
finding comprehensive sources.
So even when they do
find relevant documents,
they're not always finding
the foundational papers.
So this is where if you
are an expert in the area,
you kind of know from
experience that there
are all these foundational
papers because you
build that context and bookmark
all the important papers.
The deep research agents
do a reasonably strong job,
but they struggle to assess
the document importance
beyond whether it's relevant
to the context or not.
The surface essential facts.
So even with good
retrieval, they
don't always extract the
key information efficiently.
If you do give the
perfect sources,
so even if you say that
OK, here are all the papers
that should have been included.
Even then, if you try to get
them to extract the key facts,
even then they get
about 50% coverage.
And without knowing the exact
papers, they get lower coverage.
And then finally, if you're
trying to balance out
the synthesis quality
versus verifiability,
none of the systems
actually excels
at both the quality of
synthesis and the verifiability
in certain ways.
So you can see that being able
to refer to reference data
in the agentic evaluation
tasks is a non-trivial problem.
So it's not just about
how long the task is
or whether it's real world
economic value or not.
If you have to reference some
reference data to go look at,
it's non-trivial because you
might not get the context
that an expert has.
So you might not have that
much foundational knowledge
available.
It might not extract the
key information well enough,
so it does something.
So it's good with
human AI assistance.
And the verifiability
with respect to citations
may not have the right precision
recall trade-off that's
acceptable for that occupation.
So that roughly means-- so this
is transitioning to summarize
across all the papers.
But before I go there, let
me open up for questions just
on the DeepScholar-Bench
style of tasks.
Any questions or comments?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] seems like a much
more specific narrow thing
than the other two.
Why talk about this one
in particular as opposed
to any other [INAUDIBLE]?
So I think the broad
theme of the lecture
was very much focused
on, what do we care about
in agentic evaluations per se?
So we covered about the
length of the tasks.
We talked about the
economic value of the tasks.
But for real-world
tasks to be meaningful,
we do have to look at
knowledge bases in useful ways.
So this is a representative
task for that category.
Also for the most
foundational papers,
so I guess like
for the benchmark,
there's a list that's
collected from human experts.
These are the papers
that people with the PhDs
think the model should hit.
And then you are trying to see
how many were actually retrieved
or whatever like by
the model being tested.
I mean, at any
given point in time,
they're basically
saying yes, so there's
the human aspect of here are the
list of papers that are there.
But they're also looking
at whether it's--
I mean, it's not just the
number of the set of papers.
It's also talking about,
are you supporting
if you want to make a set
of claims, when [INAUDIBLE]
section, you're answering
the question of,
how is this work related?
So you want to make
a set of claims.
My paper is different
from these other papers.
And let's say they agree on a
set of topics with the model.
You still have to make
a bunch of claims.
And then you have to
look at the citations
and back those claims
up and then say
that your paper is different
in this particular regards.
And then this is what
being covered by the field.
So, even though the key
information coverage and then
which papers get
referenced for those
claims don't have sufficient
coverage in some ways.
So it's both retrieval quality
and then what gets written down
in terms of the key facts.
Does that make sense?
So let's try to summarize
across a different set of tasks.
And this is kind of also
addressing the question
that our classmate asked.
So in the time horizon sense,
research synthesis tasks
can be anywhere from
30 minutes to 8 hours.
But the current capability range
is somewhere around 50 minutes.
But the quality of this
horizon might still be poor.
You might still end up
with, say, 50% success rate.
So what this is roughly saying
is that if research synthesis
tasks are in long
horizon in METR,
and even though they
look good on that plot,
they might not be high quality.
In terms of economic
value, I mean,
research synthesis tasks show
up in say financial research.
They show up in a lot of
different research tasks.
So they have clear
economic value,
but they definitely
require capabilities
that current models
are not always hitting.
And oftentimes, the gaps
are coming from, say,
multi-step reasoning, from being
able to do a comprehensive job
at information gathering
to maintain verifiability
while you're synthesizing
this information.
So if you remember
from homework 3,
when you basically
combine information
from multiple
different agent calls,
you still have to maintain a
certain amount of verifiability.
And then you're
combining the context.
So there's context
engineering from a distributed
set of sources.
Maybe you did a bunch
of different tool calls.
Maybe you went and
redid the tool calls.
So all of that
information means you
have to maintain
the context in each
of those multi-step scenarios.
So we are not just
limited by task duration.
How well we do in terms
of quality of synthesis
at these time horizons
also has a lot
of headroom for improvement.
And, how does this vary
from a real world task?
So, I mean, as I said before.
So benchmarks are never perfect.
They are a
representation of what
we think is measurable today.
And so METR is
automatically scored.
There's no multi-agent
interaction.
So it's basically
targeting a set
of tasks that are single agent.
And it's not
punishing of mistakes.
And the resource
constraints, there
is no resource constraints in
terms of how much resources
can be used.
So it's basically,
in real-world,
you might actually have
more subjective constraints
in how things are scored.
You might be able to
break down the task
into multiple agents,
which might actually
lead to a better evaluation.
And then there might be
actual resource constraints
or cost of mistakes.
In the second set
of paper that we
covered called GDPVal,
which focuses very
much on economically
valuable tasks,
the key aspect there is
that the tasks are extremely
well specified, all the
contexts that the human
would have in their head
gets specified in the task.
And it's one shot.
So there is no
iterative back and forth
where you get to fix
what the model did.
And it requires
the model to have
some amount of tacit knowledge.
So it needs the knowledge to
be there already in the model.
And that gap gets covered
more by the third benchmark
that we were looking
at research synthesis.
Here the challenges are
that the models still
struggle with finding
comprehensive, high-quality
sources and surfacing key
facts and then verifying them.
And these are things that, if a
human is an expert in the field
and does this day
in and day out,
they'll be much faster
at because they just
have that context in
their head all the time.
So, what do we know now in
terms of model capabilities
and where there's
headroom for improvement?
So we kind of know
that the models
have been improving on
isolated, well-specified tasks.
If you have a set of tasks that
are well-specified and fall
in the set of domains where
the models are good at,
then they do a really good job.
Software engineering
and ML research
are two domains where we have
seen significant progress,
perhaps because as computer
scientists and computer
engineers, we tend to
understand those domains better.
So we are automating
away our own jobs.
So we definitely are
seeing these models
do a really good job in terms of
solving hour long tasks there.
And the stronger models
can generate very well
organized outputs, even if
not all parts of that outputs
are correct.
What we have lower
confidence in,
if you look at
model capabilities,
is that the model's
performance on tasks where you
need a lot of context is low.
So if you don't have the
context in the model's prompt,
then the model doesn't quite
know what to go work on.
It doesn't quite figure
out ambiguous prompts,
and just figure out what
it needs to figure out
to solve the problem.
The performance in
adversarial environments
is not necessarily great.
Overall, if you want
95% reliability,
the models are not quite there.
And generally, we have not yet
seen a lot of generalization
beyond software
and knowledge work.
Knowledge work encompasses a lot
of the digital workloads today.
We also think that the
models are still not
strong at finding comprehensive,
high quality sources when they
have to reference knowledge
bases and surface key facts,
and then verify
what they surfaced
as high accuracy and high
coverage in the knowledge base.
So all of these are still gap
areas in model capabilities.
So if we were to summarize
across the three papers
that we talked about
today, in METR,
we talked about the
seven-month doubling horizon
in terms of model capabilities.
As in the models can complete
the tasks with 50% reliability.
That time horizon has been
doubling every seven months.
And the forecast is
that say, 2028 to 2031,
it will almost be a one month.
Task can be completed
by the model.
But that view gets
contradicted in some ways
by GDPVal win rate,
which shows more
of a linear improvement
over the last two years,
where even though the win rate
for a certain set of tasks
is 48%, at the
same time, you will
see that there are
many category of tasks
that don't have high win rates.
And then the other
gap area that you see
is that a lot of
the tasks in GDPVal
actually require
context or require
looking at reference data.
And DeepScholar-Bench, the
research synthesis task
kind of shows you that
there are critical gaps when
you have to go retrieve
some set of context
or look at a knowledge base.
And generally, the quality
and the verifiability
don't quite match
up compared to what
a human would be able to do.
So in general, the reliability
and the error recovery
of the model should
continue to improve,
but the performance will
vary still over task types,
like which category of
tasks we are looking at.
So even if the models are
solving longer and longer
horizon tasks, that
doesn't necessarily
mean they're always giving
highly reliable or quality
outputs.
So we need metrics which
are duration-based, economic
value-based, and also
synthesis quality-based.
And you still need to
validate them against humans
who can solve these tasks.
OK with that, I will actually
open up for questions.
If you go back to the first
task for the [INAUDIBLE] team.
So what do you think
about the [INAUDIBLE]
it's similar to many
like Moore's law.
So I'm just curious because
you are much experts than me.
What do you think [INAUDIBLE]?
So I think there's two
answers to your question.
I mean, SWE-bench
definitely shows--
SWE-bench Verified,
for example, has
shown a really strong growth.
In general encoding
area, we will
continue to see improvements.
And still there is
a large category
of tasks which are not just
pull request-based and so on.
And these are hard tasks.
So there's a long path that
will continue to be challenging
for the longest.
I mean, Waymo, the first
[INAUDIBLE] easy to do,
and then the last
20% [INAUDIBLE].
Distributed systems
being one of the areas
in which computer science, where
it's very hard for the model
to get it right.
You've mentioned a couple
times automating [INAUDIBLE].
What is your sense of how you
expect your own work to look
different two years from now?
So I think AI timelines are
moving extremely fast in ways
where it's very hard to predict
something one year from now.
I think one of my
tasks would end up
being [INAUDIBLE] what
an AI scientist does,
and AI scientists being able to
come up with hypotheses and run
experiments and then complete
the whole loop is still
something of-- that is
our definition of AGI
is to when AI can build the next
generation of models themselves,
then we don't have to
even be in the loop.
But I don't think that
is quite there yet.
But it's definitely
been fascinating
to see the level of
progress in terms
of how the AI models do
have the knowledge base
and often are extremely
strong brainstorming partners.
So as AI co-scientist
at this point
in time, which has a better
value for a lot of the use
cases, is what I see.
I also generally feel
that in most areas,
getting reliability or the
long tail of reliability
is going to be
extremely challenging.
So that's the area in
which the last mile
is hard to get progress on.
I thought more of a
clarification question
about the beta paper.
So they talk about this concept
of 50% pass completion rate.
I was wondering if the 50%
is like an average success
rate, maybe, let's
say, let's say they're
like 100 test instances.
And then for each test
instance, AI will try 10 times.
And then you see you count
how many times that it
fails or succeeds.
And then you take the average
over the 100 times 10,
or is it more like you want to
be make sure for every task,
it has at least
50% because I feel
like the latter would be much
more stringent and harder
to achieve.
I think it's multiple
attempts for sure,
because if you remember,
we showed this plot.
So there are multiple agent
runs and it's basically
saying how many times it
completed successfully.
So you have maybe--
so, yeah, so here
let's say there are 97 tasks.
So each task, you
would calculate
a success rate of the agent.
And then you take the average
of the individual task success
rate across the 97, is
that what you think they're
doing to get the final 50%?
So yes, roughly, right?
For each horizon, they're
basically drawing these points.
And the points are--
the success rate
for each task is
coming from what percentage
of attempts were successful.
So 50% success rate
for a particular task
roughly would mean that
50% of the time, it
might come back with a
good answer, 30% maybe not.
So it's a flip of a coin.
[INAUDIBLE] so AI is
doing much better.
So it's [INAUDIBLE]
engineering job [INAUDIBLE].
OK, let's take that
off for the class.
I think the computer science
as a profession is not
going anywhere.
And if you are able to
reason for fundamentals,
that is a very
important skill to have.
AI, as you saw, needs to
figure out the context
or solve anything.
So you need to be able
to give it the context.
So that's my belief.
All right, I have a question.
What do you think are stopping
AI from tackling those long tail
problems?
Is it lack of data?
Or what else, I mean, what's
the fundamental limitations?
It's a mix of both a data
problem and a fundamental model
capabilities.
In certain cases, if you--
I think there are
several startups that
are tackling things and building
environments and whatnot,
but coming up with tasks
that are representative
and then stopgap in the
model capabilities in each
of these tasks continues to be
an area which is challenging
at this point in time.
So I think when they are
broad across categories
like, say, legal research
or financial research,
those have seen much faster
adoption and improvements.
But when they're
very, very specific,
like having enough
data to or having
the model progress in the right
model capabilities is hard.
For example, if you look at
robotics as a domain, which
is the embodied
AI stuff, there's
a whole suite of
startups that are just
going after data collection
as the primary hypothesis
to close the gap based
on top of these models.
OK.
Thank you.